{
  "title": "Algorithms - Sorting — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Sorting — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following array.<br><br>\\(\\begin{array}{|l|l|l|l|l|l|l|l|}  \\hline 23&amp;32&amp;45&amp;69&amp;72&amp;73&amp;89&amp;97 \\\\ \\hline\\end{array}\\)<br><br>\nWhich algorithm out of the following options uses the least number of comparisons (among the array elements) to sort the above array in ascending order? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Selection sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Mergesort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Insertion sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Quicksort using the last element as pivot</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Insertion sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357443/gate-cse-2021-set-1-question-9#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Of the following sort algorithms, which has execution time that is least dependant on initial ordering of the input? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Insertion sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Quick sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Merge sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Selection sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Merge sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331259/isro2020-65\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>An array of 25 distinct elements is to be sorted using quicksort. Assume that the pivot element is chosen uniformly at random. The probability that the pivot element gets placed in the worst possible location in the first round of partitioning (rounded off to 2 decimal places) is _________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.08",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302828/gate2019-cs-20#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Of the following sorting algorithms, which has a running time that is least dependent on the initial ordering of the input? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Mege Sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Insertion Sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Selection Sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Quick Sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Mege Sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213522/isro2018-66\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Given two sorted list of size m and n respectively. The number of comparisons needed the worst case by the merge sort algorithm will be: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>m-n</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>maximum of m and n</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>minimum of m and n</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>m+n-1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>m+n-1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213553/isro2018-35\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The number of swappings needed to sort the numbers 8 , 22, 7, 9, 31, 5, 13 in ascending order using bubble sort is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>11</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>12</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>13</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>10</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>10</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128694/isro2017-49\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following in-place sorting algorithms needs the minimum number of swaps? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Insertion Sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Quick Sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Heap Sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Selection Sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Selection Sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128545/isro2017-15\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Algorithm design technique used in quicksort algorithm is? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2016)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Dynamic programming</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Backtracking</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Divide and conquer</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Greedy method</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Divide and conquer</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2462/gate1994-1-19-isro2016-31\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Assume that the algorithms considered here sort the input sequences in ascending order. If the input is already in ascending order, which of the following are TRUE? <br>\nI. Quicksort runs in \\(\\Theta (n^{2})\\) time  <br>\nII. Bubblesort runs in \\(\\Theta (n^{2})\\) time <br>\nIII. Merge sort runs in \\(\\Theta (n)\\) time <br>\nIV. Insertion sort runs in \\(\\Theta (n)\\) time <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and II only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39561/gate2016-2-13#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>The worst case running times of Insertion sort, Mergesort and Quicksort, respectively, are: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta\\)(n logn), \\(\\Theta\\)(n logn), and \\(\\Theta(n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n^{2}),\\Theta(n^{2}), and \\Theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n^{2}),\\Theta(n logn), and \\Theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n^{2}),\\Theta(n logn), and \\Theta (n^{2})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n^{2}),\\Theta(n logn), and \\Theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39660/gate2016-1-13#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>If one uses straight two-way merge sort algorithm to sort the following elements in ascending order:<br>20, 47, 15, 8, 9, 4, 40, 30, 12, 17<br>then the order of these elements after second pass of the algorithm is: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>8, 9, 15, 20, 47, 4, 12, 17, 30, 40</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>8, 15, 20, 47, 4, 9, 30, 40, 12, 17</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>15, 20, 47, 4, 8, 9, 12, 30, 40, 17</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4, 8, 9, 15, 20, 47, 12, 17, 30, 40</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>8, 15, 20, 47, 4, 9, 30, 40, 12, 17</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1467/gate1999-1-14-isro2015-42\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>A machine needs a minimum of 100 sec to sort 1000 names by quick sort. The minimum time needed to sort 100 names will be approximately <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>50.2 sec</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>6.7 sec</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>72.7 sec</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>11.2 sec</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>6.7 sec</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/10595/isro2015-12\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Assume that a mergesort algorithm in the worst case takes 30 seconds for an input of size 64. Which of the following most closely approximates the maximum input size of a problem that can be solved in 6 minutes? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>256</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>512</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1024</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2048</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>512</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8480/gate2015-3-27#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Suppose you are provided with the following function declaration in the C programming language.<br><br> int partition(int a[ ], int n); <br><br> The function treats the first element of a[] as a pivot, and rearranges the array so that all elements less than or equal to the pivot is in the left part of the array, and all elements greater than the pivot is in the right part. In addition, it moves the pivot so that the pivot is the last element of the left part. The return value is the number of elements in the left part. <br>\nThe following partially given function in the C programming language is used to find the \\( k^{th}\\) smallest element in an array a[ ] of size n using the partition function. We assume \\( k \\leq n\\)<pre><code>  int kth_smallest(int a[], int n, int k)\n{\n    int left_end = partition(a,n);\n    if ( left_end+1 == k ){\n         return a[left_end];\n    }\n    if ( left_end+1 &gt; k ){\n         return kth_smallest( ________ );\n    } else {\n         return kth_smallest( ________ );\n    }\n} </code></pre><br> The missing argument lists are respectively <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(a, left_end, k) and (a+left_end+1, n-left_end-1, k-left_end-1)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(a, left_end, k) and (a, n-left_end-1, k-left_end-1)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(a+left_end+1, n-left_end-1, k-left_end-1) and (a, left_end, k)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(a, n-left_end-1, k-left_end-1) and (a, left_end, k)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>(a, left_end, k) and (a+left_end+1, n-left_end-1, k-left_end-1)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8243/gate2015-2-39#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following is the recurrence equation for the worst case time complexity of the Quicksort algorithm for sorting n ( \\(\\geq\\)2) numbers? In the recurrence equations given in the options below, c is a constant. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>T(n)=2T(n/2)+cn</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>T(n)=T(n-1)+T(1)+cn</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>T(n)=2T(n-1)+cn</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>T(n)=T(n/2)+cn</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>T(n)=T(n-1)+T(1)+cn</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8017/gate2015-1-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}